太阳
The sun...
施予光线和生命
赤道的太阳最猛烈
giver of light and life,
shines most powerfully at the Equator.
太阳在这里驱动生物丰富的区域
Here, it powers
an extraordinarily rich zone of life.
三大洲三大洋瞩目奇异的动物
Brilliant and bizarre species from
three continents... three oceans.
赤道不只是地图上的一条线
而是自然的强大力量
More than a line on a map...
Equator is a powerful force of nature.
赤道
赤道非洲
变化的挑战
赤道在加蓬海岸
The Equator meets
the western edge of Africa
和非洲西端交汇
on the coast of Gabon.
这是非洲少数森林
It's one of few places
in all of Africa
长至海岸的地方
where forests grow down
to the shore...
森林动物在这里寻找新机会
and where forest animals come
in search of new opportunity...
改变或适应可以是
成功的生存策略
To change or adapt can be
a successful survival tactic.
生存也许仰赖探索未知边界
and survival may depend on
exploring unfamiliar frontiers.
这些河马去哪里？
为什么？
Where are these Hippopotami going...
and why?
步向未知
Venturing into the unknown is
在一块经历巨变的
a recurring survival story here
on a continent
大陆上不断重复
that has undergone huge upheaval.
动物要面对改变考验
不然就难逃一死
Animals have had to meet
the 'challenge of change'... or perish.
赤道的东非是干旱草原
In Equatorial East Africa
is the arid savanna...
这种地形在赤道很罕见
such landscape is rare at the Equator.
全球赤道土地大多是潮湿森林
Equator lands around the world are
mostly forest covered... and wet.
草原已经几个月没下雨
Here, on the savanna,
it hasn't rained for months...
太阳持续的酷热晒干了地面
The unrelenting heat of the sun
has sucked the earth dry...
只有少数动物能够忍受
none but a few animals
can endure it.
能够克服酷热的是秃鹰
Riding powerful heat waves
are vultures.
它们预示死亡
They are winged
harbingers of death.
在旱季生存是最重要的事
... In the dry season,
survival is all that matters.
狮子在旱季不得不偷秃鹰的食物
In the dry season, lions are
forced to steal from vultures.
狮子在长旱季里都在草原
Lions remain on the savannah
throughout the long drought.
它们总是饥肠辘辘
Hunger is a constant companion
只能眼睁睁看着匮乏的猎食地
and they can only gaze out
on depleted hunting grounds.
汤臣瞪羚不能满足它们所需
A Thomson's gazelle
will not satisfy their needs...
但有总比没有好
but it will help.
日复一日，它们都追不到瞪羚
Day after day,
the pursuit ends in failure.
每次追捕都会耗用能量
尤其是有幼狮的雌狮
Each hunt saps energy,
especially for females with young.
母狮乳汁不多
她们的幼狮很虚弱
Mothers have little milk...
and their cubs are weak.
成年狮子一星期必须吃十公斤肉
An adult lion must eat
1 0 kilograms of meat a week...
少于十公斤它们和幼狮
就会性命垂危
any less, and they and their young
will be in peril.
九成幼狮会在旱季饿死
In the dry season,
90% of cubs may starve to death.
死也有很多方式
And death comes in other guises.
鬣狗也非常饥饿
它们会猎食幼狮
Hyenas are also desperately hungry,
and they are cub killers.
狮子旱季会留在这干旱平原上
Lions remain on this arid plain
during the dry season
因为它们的命运
和保护猎食地点相连
because their fate is linked to
protecting their hunting domain...
它们的命运
也跟快将发生的事相连
and their fate is linked to
a drama that is about to unfold...
11月清凉的贸易风开始由南吹来
In November, cool trade winds
begin to blow from the south...
动物在风吹来很久之前
就能感受到改变
Animals can sense a change long
before it happens.
大群动物迁移
Great herds are on the move,
几百万只动物开始前往
草原的湿长旅程
millions of animals begin
a long journey toward the savanna.
它们前进时乌云也紧随其后
As they approach,
so do dark heavy clouds,
乌云为干燥平原带来急需的礼物
clouds that bring a much
needed gift to the dry plain.
改变突然而且惊心动魄
骤雨也是
The change is sudden and dramatic...
and so are showers.
骤雨下了不到一小时就停止了
lt pours for less than an hour...
and stops...
下过骤雨后至少凉快一点
At least it's cooler
after these brief downpours,
动物可以喝水，水到处都是
and animals can drink,
there is water everywhere.
每天草地都淹在水里
然后慢慢晾干
Every day grasslands flood,
then slowly dry out....
几星期都会这样
this will be the pattern for
several weeks...
这地区在快到一年
最炎热的时候下雨
The rains come as the region
approaches it's hottest time of year...
在太阳移至最高点之时
as the sun advances to
its highest point...
晒裂土地的太阳
The sun that parched and
cracked the land for months
现在带来云雨
now brings clouds and rain
让尘土飞扬的平原解喝
to quench the deep thirst
of the dusty plain.
动物大迁移
The herds of
the great migration
算准丰足之时迁徙
time their journey to coincide with
this abundance.
就肉眼所见
As far as the eye can see,
新生植物
被近二百万只角马吃掉
new growth is feasted on by
close to 2 million wildebeests,
还有瞪羚和斑马
other gazelles and zebras.
动物不仅算好下雨的时候迁移
Animals not only time their
migration to the coming of the rains...
而且它们也急不及待产子
it's quickly followed by
a frenzy of births and babies.
所有小角马一个月内就出生
All wildebeest calves are
born within just one month
它们一定要学会走路
and they must quickly
find their feet
跟着母亲
to keep up with their mothers.
出生狂热越发增加了动物数量
The birth bonanza further
swells animal numbers.
赤道东非部份地方现在集合了
Parts of Equatorial East Africa
now contain
全球最多的动物
some of the greatest aggregations
of animals on the planet...
赤道东非不是一直
Equatorial Africa hasn't always
都有这么多动物
hosted such spectacular
animal numbers...
过去这里截然不同
in the past it was
a very different place.
东非长久以来
For a long time, Africa was isolated
和其他大陆隔绝
大部份森林密布
from other land masses
and mostly covered in forest...
在这些森林栖息的古老动物
后代存活至今
in these forests lived ancient animals
whose descendants survive today...
也许最出名的时期
非洲动物是大象
Perhaps the most famous of
these early Africans is the elephant.
它们的祖先是小得多的生物
lt is descended from
a much smaller creature thought
一般认为和蹄兔有关
to be related to the hyrax...
力大无穷的大象
曾经长得像这样吗？
is it possible the mighty elephant
once looked like this?
灵长类也和非洲祖先毫不相像
Primates also look nothing like
their African ancestors...
吃白蚁的奇怪食蚁兽
Where as the strange,
则六千万年来无甚改变
termite eating aardvark has
changed little in 60 million years.
约二千万年前
About 20 million years ago,
非洲经历巨变
Africa underwent
a dramatic transformation.
陆地和海洋高度改变
将欧亚和非洲拉近
Land and sea level changes brought
Africa and Eurasia closer together,
直至最终连结
until they finally connected.
大陆连结带来大量奇怪新动物
The joining of continents brought
an influx of strange new animals.
大多数栖息在森林
Most were forest dwellers...
包括野猪和奇怪的像马动物
among them were hogs
and strange horse like animals,
还有古代羚羊
as well as ancient antelopes...
随它们而来的有猎兽
and with them came predators...
包括各种猫科动物
including cats of many kind...
一些古老动物
... Some of these ancient species
brought secrets
将秘密传给下一代
that they handed on
to their descendants...
这是霍加披
森林的马
This is the Okapi,
a name that means 'forest horse'.
尽管它和马的大小和外形相同
Although it's the size
and shape of a horse,
它和长颈鹿有共同祖先
而且还有一个秘密
it shares a common ancestor...
and a secret, with the giraffe.
非洲林羚保留了
African Bush Bucks retain
欧洲祖先原始外形
the primitive shape of
their European forbears...
但它们也得到
but they also inherited
a very special gift
栖息森林的
祖先的特别礼物
from their forest
dwelling ancestors.
最初的凑羊有多个腔室的胃部
The first antelopes
had multi chambered stomachs.
胃部含有细菌
They contained bacteria,
可以消化低营养植物
that allowed them to
digest low-nutrient plants
其他食草动物吃不下的
that other herbivores could not eat.
它们胃部这秘密武器
This 'secret weapon'
stomach would
有一天会改变赤道附近的生物
one day transform life
near the Equator...
但森林覆盖大陆
but while forests
covered the continent,
这些动物机会不多
there was little opportunity
for these animals.
但它们的命运由非洲
其他事情决定
However their fate would be
determined by other events in Africa
其中一件事就是地壳碎裂
and one was
particularly earth shattering.
约三千万年前，东非裂开
About 30 millions years ago,
East Africa was torn apart.
一座大峡谷渐渐成形
Slowly, a great valley opened
and highlands
巨大火山力量挤出了高地
were thrust up by
enormous volcanic forces.
几百万年以来大裂谷
Over millions of years
The Great Rift Valley spread north
南北扩张了4500多公里
and south for over four thousand
five hundred kilometers.
埃塞俄比亚高地升至三千米
The Ethiopian Highlands
rose up to 3,000 meters...
阻挡西方的雨云
blocking rain bearing clouds
from the west,
在东非形成雨影带
creating a rain shadow area
in East Africa.
陆地变得干燥，雨林渐渐消失
As the land became drier,
rain forests slowly vanished...
草地出现了
and grasslands appeared.
草慢慢覆盖东非较干旱部份
Grasses slowly covered
the drier parts of East Africa...
这些新草地会大大改变
赤道的生物
These new grasslands would
profoundly change life at the Equator.
植物是最先改变的
And first change was to
the plants themselves...
太阳靠近赤道的
Being close to the Equator,
强大能量养活一群
the intense power of
the sun favoured a group of grasses
称为“碳四”的草
called "Carbon 4" or C4 plants.
这些草的方法令人惊讶
These grasses possess
将阳光和二氧化碳
a revolutionary pathway
for changing sunlight
变成糖份
and carbon dioxide gas
into sugars.
大多数草里
In most grasses,
进行光合作用的细胞
the cells that carry out
photosynthesis,
靠近叶子的高表面
are near the leaf's upper surface.
碳四植物的细胞紧紧聚在
鞘细胞附近
In C4 plants, they are packed
tightly around sheath cells.
二氧化碳进入叶子
...and as CO2 enters the leaf,
外细胞会聚合二氧化碳
the outer cells of this bundle,
concentrate the carbon dioxide.
这是碳四植物的秘密武器
This is the C4 plant's secret weapon...
叶子像有涡轮增压器的引擎
the leaf's like an engine
with a turbocharger...
叶子快速制造糖份
lt rapidly manufactures sugars
生长率比其他草快最多八倍
and growth rates are up to 8 times
faster than other grasses.
赤道阳光的能量增加
... and as the power of
Equatorial sunlight increases,
光合作用几乎可以无限量增加
so photosynthesis can
increase almost indefinitely...
整个系统包裹在坚硬外果心
The whole system is
encased in a tough outer core,
让这些草难以消化
and this made these grasses
very difficult to digest.
C4草在
C4 grasses out competed
东非最炎热的地方
取代了其他草
and replaced other grasses
in the hottest parts of East Africa...
但这些新草地很多食草动物
But these new "grasslands"
were tough,
视作难以下咽的荒地
inedible wastelands for
many grass eaters...
但有一群动物
however,
the new plants proved to be
对新植物趋之若鹜
highly desirable for
one group of animals...
几百万年以来
For millions of years,
这些动物
就栖身在森林
these animals had been
forest dwellers,
但新草地扩张
but as the new grasslands spread,
它们只好吃这些
they emerged to graze
on these tough,
低营养硬植物
nutrient poor plants.
这种动物叫做有蹄动物
The animals are called ungulates,
a name that means 'hoof'...
但因为可以消化草
but being able to digest grasses...
因此又名反刍动物
gave rise to another name...
ruminants.
它们叫做反刍动物
因为它们的超级胃而得名
They're called ruminants,
in honor of their 'super stomachs'...
它们遗传了祖先的三室胃
They'd inherited a 3 chambered
stomach from their ancestors...
但即使有三室胃
也不足以消化碳四草
but even this was not adequate
for the job of digesting C4 grasses.
这些硬植物需要更厉害的消化
These tough plants required
more powerful digestion...
食草动物可能在干旱草地上
It's probable that it was
on the dry grasslands
演化出新的胃
that grazers evolved
a new model of stomach...
这种胃有一个称为瘤胃的大室
lt had a large extra chamber
called the rumen,
草先在这里分解
where the grass
is first broken down.
消化的媒介是微生物
The agents of digestion
are microbes.
它们攻击草的硬细胞壁
They attack the grass's
tough cell walls,
释出糖份和维他命
releasing sugars and vitamins...
但这只是第一步
but this is only the first stage.
部份消化的草由第二个胃
泵回口中
Partly digested grasses are pumped
from the second stomach
再嘴嚼后加快
back to the mouth and
chewed again to speed up the next stage
第三个胃里
发生的下一步骤
that takes place in the 3rd stomach.
草液在这里喂养细菌
细菌快速繁殖
Here, the grassy broth feeds bacteria
that multiply quickly and dramatically.
最后食物流到
Finally, the contents move to
最后一个腔室
也就是真胃
the last chamber
which are the true stomach...
这就是最后消化的地方
This is where final digestion
takes place...
现在动物不仅是消化草
By now, the animal
is not only digesting grass,
也是消化高蛋白质的细菌
it's also digesting
a high protein diet of bacteria.
反刍动物的超级胃
The ruminant 'super stomach'
让一些食草动物长得大而有力
has allowed some herbivores to
grow large... and powerful....
现代反刍动物约在二百万年前
在非洲出现
Modern ruminants arose in Africa
about 2 million years ago.
水牛渐渐长成最大
The buffalo has grown to
be one of the biggest
和最笨重的反刍动物之一
and most lumbering
of ruminants...
但其他反刍动物体积和速度
大相迳庭
but others differ hugely
in size and speed.
汤臣羚羊是短跑好手
Thomson's gazelles
are lightly built sprinters.
角马却是长跑好手
Wildebeests are marathon runners,
但草原上还有很多
速度飞快的动物
but there are many
other swift athletes of the savanna.
最大的是长颈鹿
The biggest of all is the giraffe...
反刍动物现在占据很多
不同栖息地，生活方式五花八门
Ruminants now occupy
many different habitats and lifestyles.
东非山羚仍然栖息在
陡斜突出石地
Klippspringers keep to
steep rocky outcrops...
Gerunuk 喜欢灌木丛地区
Areas of low bush and shrubs
are favoured by Gerunuks.
小羚在最茂密的灌木丛深处觅食
Tiny Dik Dik feed deep inside
the thickest bush.
快速灵活的高角羚
是其中一种平原瞪羚
Fast, agile lmpala are
one of many open plain gazelles.
獐羚是隐秘的湿地栖息者
Reedbucks are
secretive wetland dwellers...
水羚也是
as are waterbucks
Nyara较喜欢半沙漠
The preferred range of Nyara
is semi desert...
Oryx则栖息在
最干旱的沙漠地区
whereas, Oryx inhabit
the very driest desert areas.
非洲有125种羚羊
There are 1 25 species of antelope
in Africa...
占了全球羚羊总数近九成
almost 90% of the world total.
它们以壮观的方式征服了草地
They've conquered the grasslands
in spectacular fashion...
动物的大小由半米到五米都有
animals range in size from
half a meter to 5 meter giants;
有独行动物也有几百万只的羊群
from loners to herds of millions...
反刍动物的胃有其他好处
The ruminant stomach
has other advantages...
草消化得较慢而且彻底
grass is digested more slowly
and thoroughly,
因为胃部较有效率
and because it is more efficient,
羚羊不需要经常吃草
Antelopes don't have to
graze constantly...
它们察觉到猎兽逼近
When an approaching enemy
is detected...
就会突然迅速逃走
escape is swift and sudden.
兽群有很多眼睛、耳朵
和鼻子感应危险
the herd has many eyes,
ears and noses to sense danger...
这塑造了猎食它们的主要敌手
猫科动物的进化
and this has shaped the evolution of
their main predators, the cats.
羚羊进化时
As antelopes evolved,
猫科动物也变成更致命的猎兽
so cats changed to become
more deadly predators.
一头豹在树顶监视猎物
A leopards spies its prey
from the treetops.
它的祖先或许也栖息在树上
Its ancestors were
probably tree dwellers too.
在草地上，
它是无声的影子…
In the grass,
it's silent as a shadow...
慢慢走近目标
slowly working its way into range.
豹不会立即杀死猎物
The leopard
doesn't kill immediately...
可能会有其他豹偷它的食物
there may be others
that would steal it...
树是最安全的地方
the home tree is the safest place.
豹学会了蹑手蹑脚
The leopard has developed stealth
骗过羚羊对危险的敏锐感觉
to outwit the antelope's finely
tuned sense of danger.
鬣豹是开阔草原的猫科动物
The cheetah is
a cat of the open savanna...
这里没有藏身之地
out here, there's nowhere to hide...
它用不同方式猎食
它靠速度
it uses a different tactic to
hunt prey... it uses speed.
如果鬣豹在猎物看到它之前追捕
If it can begin the chase
before its prey sees it,
就会占有优势
the cheetah has the advantage.
在非洲，鬣豹的体型
In Africa, the cheetah's body shape
渐渐能够
追得上飞奔的小羚羊
became adapted to run down small,
fast antelopes.
它的时速达110公里
Exploding to reach speeds of
110 kilometers per hour,
是全球陆上最快的动物
it's the fastest land animal
in the world.
鬣豹的身体变成流线型
It's body became streamlined,
爪子就像钩
轻、有弹性、有力
its claws work as spikes,
it is light, flexible and powerful.
草地增加了快速的小瞪羚
The grasslands have boosted
the number of small fast gazelles...
鬣豹以高速追上它们
and cheetahs use blinding
speed to outrun them.
非洲所有猫科动物中
Of all Africa's cats,
狮子受赤道太阳的影响最大
the lion has been most shaped
by the Equatorial sun.
狮子会以血缘聚居，称为族群
Lions live in family groups
called prides...
它们是全球唯一群居的猫科动物
they are the only truly social cats
in the world.
它们也是草原上最大的猫科动物
They are also the biggest cats
on the savanna.
雄狮一米多高，重260公斤
Males stand over a meter high
and weigh 260 kilograms...
尽管雄狮体型庞大
yet, despite their size,
它们仍是狮群的边缘份子
males remain on the margins
of lion society.
狮群是大家庭
A lion pride is
an extended family of several
有几只到12只雌狮和幼狮
to dozen females and their young.
这是雌狮的社群
lt is a society of females...
全都平等，全都在相若时间繁殖
all are equal, all breed at
around the same time...
这狮群里最老的雌狮
戴着无线电追踪圈
The oldest female in this pride
wears a radio tracking collar.
它是头领，有很多有用的
经验和知识
She's the leader; she has much
useful experience and knowledge...
雄狮的角色是
The male's role is to defend
守卫狮群的地盘
和生育下一代
the pride's territory
and father the cubs.
狮子的庞大体型
The lion's imposing size
和独特社会结构
是有原因的
and unique social structure
exists for a reason...
非洲最大的猫科动物
the biggest cats in Africa,
集体捕食
一些最大的食草动物
work in groups to hunt some of
the largest plant eaters...
但即使群猎也不一定成功
Yet, even working together
does not guarantee success...
猎物通常在远处就看到狮子
prey animals often see lions
from a long distance...
所以狮子大多数会在晚上捕猎
so most hunting is done after dark.
晚上是杀戮时间
很多动物都很活跃
Night is the killing time...
when many animals are active.
晚上限制了猎物的视力
Darkness restricts the vision of
prey animals
狮子藉机走近
allowing lions to get closer...
但它们晚上猎食主要因为较凉快
but they hunt at night mainly
because it is cooler.
猎食耗费大量能量
Hunting uses a lot of energy...
狮子在烈日下很容易体温过高
lions easily overheat
under the blazing sun...
它们较喜欢晚上猎食
night kills are preferred.
猎食狮群组织严密
A lion hunting party
is highly organized.
它们发现一群猎物后
Once a group of prey animals
is identified,
就会悄悄慢慢包围
they are slowly
and quietly surrounded...
所有狮子都各就各位
When all lions are in position,
有一两只会故意让猎物看到
one or two will
make themselves visible.
瞪羚很快跑开
The gazelles move quickly away...
但陷阱已经布下了
but the trap is set...
它们正向等待的狮群跑去
they run into the waiting jaws
of the group.
猎物会由狮群分食
The kill is shared
among members of the pride...
狮群各有自己的猎食地盘
Each pride has a hunting territory,
雄狮的任务是保护狮群和地盘
and the constant mission for
the male is to protect both pride
抵抗可能会推翻它的雄狮
and territory against other males
that would overthrow him.
地盘可以延伸至100平方公里
The territory can extend
over 1 00 sq kilometers...
它的巨吼声地盘
大部份地方都听得到
And his loud roar
can be heard over most of it.
它巡行时会在边缘留下气味
As he patrols, he leaves
scent marks along the borders.
猎食成功不一定代表享用猎物
A successful hunt does not
always mean enjoying the kill...
雌狮进食时被一群鬣狗包围
As they feed, the females are
surrounded by a band of hyenas.
鬣狗就体型来说
有非洲最有力的牙齿
For their size, hyenas have
the strongest jaws in Africa...
对它们不能掉以轻心
而且它们的数量比狮子多
they're not to be taken lightly...
and they outnumber the lions.
雌狮别无他法
只好放弃辛苦得来的食物
The females have no choice
but to give up their hard won meal.
但现在雄狮回来了
But now the male returns...
鬣狗的胜利只是昙花一现
The Hyenas victory is short lived...
数目多敌不过生气的雄狮
superior numbers are
no match for an angry male lion.
它回来的时候仍然怒气未消
And when he returns,
his mood has not improved...
保护的代价是猎物归它所有
The price of protection is
that he takes over the kill.
其中一只捕猎的雌狮离开了
One of the hunting females
now departs.
她和养育狮群所有幼儿的雌狮
She returns to the kill
with the nursing females
回到食物附近
who are caring for
all the cubs of the pride.
雄狮让幼狮和它一起吃猎物
The male allows the young cubs
to feed alongside him...
它不打算让雌狮这样做
It's a privilege he is not prepared to
extend to the female.
雄狮认为幼狮的安全和生存
是最重要的
For the male, the safety and
survival of the cubs is most important
它们遗传了它的基因
as they carry his genes.
雄狮恃势先吃猎物
The male may bully his way
to first helping of the kill,
但雌狮控制狮群
but the females control the pride...
它们的主要工作是保持狮群强壮
Their major imperative
is a strong society...
和保存它们的猎食地盘
and to retain their hunting territory.
狮子猎食地盘由雌狮传给女儿
The lions hunting territory is passed
from females to their daughters...
年轻雄狮成年后一定要离开狮群
Young males must leave
the pride once they reach maturity...
这样可以防止近亲交配
保持狮群实力
this keeps the pride strong by
removing the risk of inbreeding.
雄狮血统由一个狮群
传至另一个狮群
Male blood moves
from pride to pride.
年轻独雄狮称为流浪狮
Young lone males are called Nomads...
这流浪狮过去一个月
this nomad has
spent the previous month
独自游荡和猎食
wandering and hunting by himself...
它只有两岁，刚长出鬃毛
He's just 2 years of age,
with just the beginnings of a mane.
它太年轻了，不能挑战成年雄狮
He's still far too young to
challenge a full grown male.
流浪狮一般会跟随着狮群边缘
Nomads often lurk
on the fringes of prides...
它们会频频挑战
They mount frequent challenges,
测试主导雄狮的力量和速度
to test the strength and
speed of the dominant males.
有一天，狮群的雄狮会反应迟钝
虚弱得无法自卫
One day, the pride male will not be fast
or strong enough to defend himself...
但那一天尚未到来
but that day is not today.
这流浪狮会回来
它会一直尝试
This nomad will return,
he will keep trying...
如果它独自能够生存的话
if he can survive out there
on his own.
流浪狮这阶段确保力量
传给所有狮子
The "Nomad" strategy ensures that
strength is bred into all lions...
面对旱季困苦的力量
strength to face
the hardships of the dry season...
还有猎杀草原上
大食草动物的力量
and strength to hunt large
herbivores on the savanna.
有一种食草动物
比任何动物都要高
There's one plant eater
that's taller than all the rest...
长颈鹿身型庞大
狮子很少攻击它们
Giraffe are so big;
they're rarely attacked by Lions.
长颈鹿有反刍动物的胃
但它们不在草原上吃草
The giraffe has a ruminant stomach
but it does not graze the savanna...
它的长颈让它吃得到
金合欢的叶子
Its long neck gives it
access to acacia trees,
少数能在这环境下生存的树
one of very few trees that
can survive these conditions.
金合欢叶子营养丰富
Acacia leaves are rich in nutrients...
但受到绝佳保护
要吃的话要花点心思
but they're well protected...
eating is a delicate art.
长颈鹿能轻易碰到这些树
Giraffes can easily
reach high into the trees...
但它们要弯身吃草或喝水
就有点困难
but they experience some difficulty
bending to graze or drink.
长颈的一个问题是控制血压
One problem from having such a long neck
is controlling blood pressure...
尤其是流到脑部的血压
specifically,
the pressure of blood to the brain.
长颈鹿站直时
When standing upright,
心脏一定要将血压
the giraffe's heart
must raise blood pressure to
提升至人类的一倍
more than twice human pressure
才能将血推上颈部和头部
in order to push the blood up
the neck and into the head.
但它弯下身子
But when it bends down,
所有压力该会突然使血涌到头部
all that pressure should suddenly
rush blood to the head and potentially
可能会流血致命
cause fatal hemorrhage...
但事实上不会
but it doesn't.
因为长颈鹿脑部下
有特别的器官
That's because, a giraffe has a
special blood pressure control organ
控制血压
just beneath its brain.
这结构称为网状海绵体
是血管网络
The structure, called a "wondernet",
is a network of blood vessels.
血液涌到头部的时候
As blood rushes to the head,
网状海绵体吸收增加的血液流量
the wondernet absorbs
the increased flow
像海绵一样膨胀
and swells like a sponge.
膨胀的时候，网状海绵体
As it swells,
arteries between wondernet
和脑部之间的动脉
像水喉一样扭曲
and brain bend and crimp
like a water hose,
进一步减少血液流量
further reducing blood flow.
网状海绵体让长颈鹿
成为赤道最高的动物
The wondernet enabled
the giraffe to become
可以吃到营养最丰富的食物
the tallest animal of the Equator
and reach for the richest food...
但这是怎样发生的？
but how did it come about?
可能是草地扩张
lt is likely that as grasslands spread,
巨型长颈鹿
the giant giraffe evolved from
快速自森林短颈祖先进化
a short necked forest ancestor
very quickly...
因为它从森林带来的一个秘密
because of a secret it
brought from the forest...
那秘密仍可以找到
And that secret is still found
在刚果东部最偏远的地方
in the remotest parts
of Eastern Congo...
隐藏秘密的是长颈鹿的
森林近似动物
it lives on in
the giraffe's forest relative.
这种近似动物高度
只及长颈鹿1/3
This relative stands only
one third of the giraffe's height
称为霍加披
and is the forest horse,
the Okapi.
短颈霍加披
The short necked okapi
不需要调节血压
doesn't need to regulate
it's blood pressure,
但它也有网状海绵体
yet, it also has a wondernet...
这就能解释长颈鹿怎样进化
and this could explain
how the giraffe evolved.
欧卡皮鹿和长颈鹿有共同祖先
古麟动物
Okapi and giraffe have
a common ancestor... the Paleotragus.
如果能够证明它也有网状海绵体
If it could be proved that
it too had a 'wondernet',
就能解开森林古麟动物
it would solve the mystery of how
the Paleotragus of the forest
怎样快速变成草原长颈鹿的谜团
could so rapidly become
the giraffe of the savanna...
可能长颈鹿预先适应了草原生活
It's possible that the Giraffe was
pre adapted to life on the savanna...
但非洲一种土生动物
but one of Africa's original inhabitants
went down aquite different path
在赤道
这干燥地区存活的方式大相径庭
to survive life on
this arid region of the Equator...
它改变脑袋和身体
lt changed its brain
as well as its body.
大象没有反刍动物的胃
Elephants don't
have ruminant stomachs...
它们怎样抵挡酷热和干旱？
so, how do they beat the heat...
and the dry?
它们的方法是扩大身形
they do it by being
'super sized'.
较小的动物在旱季会挨饿
In dry seasons,
smaller animals will starve whereas,
较大的动物，例如大象
larger animals, like elephants,
吃的食物不及每单位体重
更有可能活下来
eat less food per unit of body weight,
and are more likely to survive.
但大象的脑部也会生长
But elephants also
grew their brains.
它们用牙当作剥树皮的工具
吸取营养
They use their tusks as a tool to
peel away tree bark for nutrients.
它们在旱季
In the dry season,
记得
最好的觅食场在哪里
they remember where
the best feeding grounds are...
将知识传给下一代
and pass this knowledge
on to their offspring.
大象及不上反刍动物
Elephants might be less efficient
将植物变成能量的效率
than ruminants at turning plants
into energy...
它们生存是靠智力和体型
their survival is
based on brain power and size.
河马也是巨物
Hippopotomi are also giants.
它们一天大多数时间都在湖泊里
They spend much of the day
in rivers and lakes,
躲避猛烈阳光
to protect themselves from
the sun's powerful rays...
粉红色不是晒伤
the pink colour is not sunburn
而是皮肤渗出来的防晒油
but a form of sunblock that
they exude onto their skins...
水也能节省能量
The water also saves energy,
可以支撑它们厚皮身体的重量
it helps support the enormous weight
of their thick skinned bodies...
它们和大象一样
没有反刍动物的胃
Like elephants,
they don't have ruminant stomachs.
它们也会扩大身型
They too have increased body size
改善能量运用和生存机会
to improve energy efficiency
and their chances of survival.
河马从没有断绝过
与水的亲密关系
Hippos have never shaken off
their strong bond with water...
它们远离湖泊的话就活不成
they cannot survive
beyond rivers and lakes.
但和草原很多动物不同
Yet unlike many animals of the savanna,
它们正面对改变的考验
they are meeting
the challenge of change...
远在东非干旱平原之外
far beyond the dry plains
of East Africa.
沿赤道西行
Moving west on the Equator,
在草原和
非洲的大西洋海岸之间
between the savanna and
Africa's Atlantic sea coast,
有几片森林、湿地和草地
there's a mosaic of forest,
wetland and grassland...
这是赤道非洲草原出现前的面貌
This is what much of Equatorial Africa
looked like before the savanna existed.
帮助维持这斑驳地形的
... And helping maintain
this patchwork landscape
是一种叫做森林农夫的动物
is an animal called
the farmer of the forest.
红河猪一般穿梭森林和草地之间
Red river hogs regularly commute
between forest and grassland.
它们带着森林的种子散布草上
From the forest, they bring seeds
that they spread on the grass...
红河猪不仅吃生长的种子
Red River Hogs not only eat
the seedlings that grow up...
也遍布森林
but they also spread the forest.
森林大象身形是草原大象的一半
Forest elephants are half the size
of those on the savanna...
森林里较凉快，食物较充足
life in the forest is cooler,
food is more abundant,
它们不需要长得很大
they do not need to be giants...
但它们总是寻找新食物
But they are always
seeking new sources of food...
雨季时
and during the rainy season,
食欲让它们前往海边
their appetite draws them
toward the sea.
它们路经的是交缠的红树林
In their path, is a tangled
forest of mangrove trees?
这些树有长种子豆荚
生长在泻湖边缘
These trees with long seed pods,
fringe the edges of lagoons...
这些泻湖也有河马
and in these lagoons,
there are hippopotami.
这些河马和草原上的看来一样
These Hippos may look just
the same as those on the savanna,
但它们的行为非常不同
but their behavior is very different...
它们也被吸引到海边来
they too are drawn to the sea...
但原因至今未明
but for reasons that
remain a mystery.
动物来到海岸
Animals come to the sea shore,
赤道和非洲西岸相交的地方
也就是加蓬
where the Equator meets
the western coast of Africa, in Gabon...
森林水牛为何来这里？
Why do forest buffalo come here?
它们来这里是为了食物
They come here for food.
雨水将海岸森林的植物
The rain washes vegetation
from the coastal forest
冲出海
再冲回沙滩上
out into the ocean
and back onto the beaches...
动物找寻的红树林种子豆荚
animals seek out Mangrove seed pods
含有大量矿物质
that contain high concentrations
of minerals.
大象也知道这特别的食物来源
Elephants also know of
this special food source...
它们将这件事告诉小象
and they pass this knowledge
onto their young.
但沙滩上还有令人意外的来客
But there is another surprise
appearance at the beach.
河马来到海岸
但不是为了吃红树林豆荚
Hippos come to the coast...
but not to eat mangrove pods.
河马母子看来被吸引到海洋来
A Hippo mother and baby
seem attracted to the ocean.
看到它们离开河流感觉奇怪
It's strange to see them
away from rivers and lakes.
但它们在这里泰然自若
Yet, they seem at home here,
小河马完全淹没在浪花里
the baby is completely
submerged by the surf.
是什么驱使它们来这里？
What draws them to the sea?
也许它们游进海洋洗掉寄生虫
Perhaps they swim in
the ocean to wash off parasites.
它们借盐水的浮力在海岸迁移吗？
... do they use the buoyancy of
salt water to travel along the coast?
还是吃生在海浪区的海洋植物？
...or do they feed on sea plants
that grow in the surf zone?
没有人知道为什么它们来这里
No one knows why they come here.
只有加蓬的卢安哥河马
才会在海洋游泳
Only the hippos of Loango
in Gabon swim in the ocean.
在古代
In ancient times,
状似河马的动物
入海后变成了鲸鱼
hippopotamus like animals went
down to the sea and became whales...
也许游泳的河马在这陌生的地域
Perhaps swimming hippos,
on this unfamiliar frontier,
全新动物进化的开始
are the beginning of what could
become totally different animals,
是几万年后
tens of thousands years from now.
我们在加蓬海浪中
看到了进化过程吗？
Are we are seeing evolution
in action in the surf of Gabon?
非洲的赤道还有其他
And are there
other evolutionary experiments
进化实验在别处发生吗？
happening elsewhere
on Africa's Equator.
加蓬和刚果的森林
黑暗而且寸步难移
The jungles of Gabon and Congo
are dark and impenetrable...
但在某些地方森林伸展成
称为Bal的宽广湿地
but in places they open out into
broad wetlands called "bai".
肉质草和矿物质丰富的球茎
在这里生长
Succulent grasses and bulbs rich
in minerals grow here...
森林动物来此寻找这些植物
and forest animals emerge to
search out these plants...
其中有西低地猩猩
among them, west lowland gorillas.
这些猩猩不喜欢水
会尽可能避开水
These gorillas don't like the water
and will avoid it if possible...
但得到这些珍贵植物的欲求
太强烈
but the drive to
get these precious plants
一些猩猩会克服它们的厌恶
leads some gorillas to
overcome this dislike.
这只猩猩不仅泡在水里
Not only is this gorilla
immersing itself in the water
还挺直走路
but it is walking upright...
水的浮力帮它垂直站立
The buoyancy of water
helps it stay upright...
它还会走路，举起双手
and it walks, arms raised,
像个不情愿的洗澡者，不想弄湿
like a reluctant bather,
not wanting to get wet.
用双腿走路令人神往
It's tempting to imagine that this is
想像我们的非洲祖先就是这样
how our African ancestors
began walking on two legs...
这里如果未来气候
或其他情况改变
... and if climate or other conditions
change here in the future...
也许步行的猩猩生存的机会会较大
perhaps a walking gorilla
will be better able to survive.
但改变已经发生了
But change is already happening...
在东面远处，动物已经改变了
应付酷热
further east, animals are already
changing to cope with extreme heat.
肯亚察沃国家公园
Tsavo National Park Kenya,
位处低海拔
温度极高
is at low altitude and
has very high temperatures.
狮子勉强生存
Here, lions live
at their limit of survival.
土地在表面下较凉
The earth is cooler
beneath the surface...
温度上升时它们尝试避开热力
they try to avoid heat
as temperatures soar.
阴凉处温度近摄氏40度
In the shade it is nearly 40...
空旷地方近50度
out in the open it's close to
50 degrees Celsius.
这里的狮子一般在晚上猎食
Lions here, usually hunt at night,
但如果猎物走得太近
它们就会难抵本能
but if prey wanders too close,
they cannot resist their instincts.
在酷热下制服水牛极耗体力
To bring down a buffalo in this heat
is hugely taxing of energy...
狮子很容易体温过高
Lions overheat very easily...
如果它们体温上升
就会有虚脱和死亡的危险
if their body temperatures rise
they risk heat exhaustion and death.
水牛很快就死了
Death comes quickly for the buffalo,
喉咙被咬，阻碍了气流
和血液流动
a throat bite constricts air
and blood flow.
杀死猎物后
After the kill,
狮子一定要找遮阴处
休息后才进食
the lions must seek shade and rest
before they can begin to eat.
白天猎食可引致狮子虚脱
A daytime hunt can induce heat
exhaustion among these animals...
但察沃的雄狮
有克服酷热的另一方法
but in Tsavo, male lions have
another strategy for beating the heat.
这里的雄狮鬃毛稀少
Male lions here have
greatly reduced manes.
雄狮的鬃毛会增加体温
A lion's mane raises body temperature...
为了适应
So, they have adapted to be
它们除去象徵权威的鬃毛
without their traditional symbols
of dominance.
雄狮头领仍能看得出来
它们的鬃毛较暗
Dominant males can still be identified
their short manes are darker.
如果赤道更热
If it gets even hotter at the Equator,
短鬃毛的狮子就会随处可见
lions with short manes could
become a more familiar sight...
草原上的日出
Dawn on the savanna...
新的一天，经过另一夜杀戮
A new day,
after another night of killing.
几百万年来
Over millions of years,
赤道的东非经历剧变
Equatorial East Africa has
undergone profound changes...
东非的动物适应和存活下来
its animals have adapted...
and survived...
每天猎食动物和猎物间的
and every day that struggle
to survive continues
求生争斗继续
in battles between predator and prey.
东非是赤道上独一无二的地方
East Africa is like no other place
on the Equator...
草原上多姿多采的生物
The incredible diversity of life
on the savanna has arisen
在无情干旱缺水的季节里生生不息
from merciless seasons of
dryness and thirst...
拜赤道太阳的酷热所赐
inflicted by the intense heat of
the Equatorial sun.